Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC.
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- Oversize, 1844–1952
  - consent of all the other sects, about 1888; loc.06038; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box OV 11, Folder 1888, "Elias Hicks")
    One page of a late draft, probably the printer's copy, of the essay Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, which was first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Whitman planned to write an essay about Elias Hicks for many years. While finishing preparations for the printing of November Boughs, Whitman told Horace Traubel, "Some of these bits were written as many as thirty years ago. Some of them I have written within the past year. They are a miscellaneous lot but they all belong in the same stream." (See Traubel, With Walt Whitman in Camden, 2: 42.) The present manuscript is stored together with many other manuscripts on the topics of Elias Hicks and Quakerism. Those that directly contributed to the published essay are described separately. Those whose relationship to the published essay are unclear are not included at this stage of our work.
  - The division took place, about 1888; loc.06070; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box OV 11, Folder 1888, "Elias Hicks")
    The writing on this small scrap, regarding the so-called "Hicksite Separation" within the Religious Society of Friends, forms part of a note, headed Note.—The Separation, included in the essay Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks. This essay was first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Whitman planned to write an essay about Elias Hicks for many years. While finishing preparations for the printing of November Boughs, Whitman told Horace Traubel, "Some of these bits were written as many as thirty years ago. Some of them I have written within the past year. They are a miscellaneous lot but they all belong in the same stream." (See Traubel, With Walt Whitman in Camden, 2: 42.) The present manuscript is stored together with many other manuscripts on the topics of Elias Hicks and Quakerism. Those that directly contributed to the published essay are described separately. Those whose relationship to the published essay are unclear are not included at this stage of our work.
  - The Hicksite separation appears, about 1888; loc.06058; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box OV 11, Folder 1888, "Elias Hicks")
    The information on this small scrap was used for a note, headed Note.—The Separation, included in the essay Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks. This essay was first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Whitman planned to write an essay about Elias Hicks for many years. While finishing preparations for the printing of November Boughs, Whitman told Horace Traubel, "Some of these bits were written as many as thirty years ago. Some of them I have written within the past year. They are a miscellaneous lot but they all belong in the same stream." (See Traubel, With Walt Whitman in Camden, 2: 42.) The present manuscript is stored together with many other manuscripts on the topics of Elias Hicks and Quakerism. Those that directly contributed to the published essay are described separately. Those whose relationship to the published essay are unclear are not included at this stage of our work.
  - Instructive, recurring back, about 1888; loc.06084; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box OV 11, Folder 1888, "Elias Hicks")
    This manuscript about the life of George Fox, written in ink with some corrections in pencil, appears to be a draft introduction for the section headed George Fox (and Shakspere) in the essay Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks. This essay was first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Whitman abandoned the approach to his topic that is suggested in the first paragraph of the manuscript, but the paragraph indicated by the pointing hand, at the bottom of the manuscript, contains the kernel of a key paragraph in the published version. Whitman planned to write an essay about Elias Hicks for many years. While finishing preparations for the printing of November Boughs, Whitman told Horace Traubel, "Some of these bits were written as many as thirty years ago. Some of them I have written within the past year. They are a miscellaneous lot but they all belong in the same stream." (See Traubel, With Walt Whitman in Camden, 2: 42.) The present manuscript is stored together with many other manuscripts on the topics of Elias Hicks and Quakerism. Those that directly contributed to the published essay are described separately. Those whose relationship to the published essay are unclear are not included at this stage of our work.
  - Though all the breeds, about 1868; loc.06086; xxx.00524; xxx.00978; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box OV 11, Folder 1888, "Elias Hicks")
    The manuscript fragment on the recto of this leaf appears to have been drafted for the unpublished essay Orbic Literature, which Whitman combined with two essays published in The Galaxy (Democracy [ December 1867 ] and Personalism [ May 1868 ]) as Democratic Vistas in 1871. Democratic Vistas was reprinted in Two Rivulets ( 1876 ), Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ), Democratic Vistas, and Other Papers ( 1888 ), and Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The writing on the verso, concerning George Fox and Quakerism, is part of an apparently unrelated two-page manuscript.
  - 1645–6, about 1888; loc.06010; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box OV 11, Folder 1888, "Elias Hicks")
    These notes are based on Whitman's reading of the third volume of George L. Craik and Charles Macfarlane's The Pictorial History of England (New York: Harper & Brothers, 1848). He incorporated some of this information into his essay Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, which was first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Whitman planned to write an essay about Elias Hicks for many years. While finishing preparations for the printing of November Boughs, Whitman told Horace Traubel, "Some of these bits were written as many as thirty years ago. Some of them I have written within the past year. They are a miscellaneous lot but they all belong in the same stream." (See Traubel, With Walt Whitman in Camden, 2: 42.) The present manuscript is stored together with many other manuscripts on the topics of Elias Hicks and Quakerism. Those that directly contributed to the published essay are described separately. Those whose relationship to the published essay are unclear are not included at this stage of our work.
  - opening of George Fox, about 1888; loc.06018; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box OV 11, Folder 1888, "Elias Hicks")
    A one-page draft fragment, heavily revised, related to the George Fox (and Shakspere) section of Whitman's 1888 essay Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, first published in November Boughs and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Whitman planned to write an essay about Elias Hicks for many years. While finishing preparations for the printing of November Boughs, Whitman told Horace Traubel, "Some of these bits were written as many as thirty years ago. Some of them I have written within the past year. They are a miscellaneous lot but they all belong in the same stream." (See Traubel, With Walt Whitman in Camden, 2: 42.) The present manuscript is stored together with many other manuscripts on the topics of Elias Hicks and Quakerism. Those that directly contributed to the published essay are described separately. Those whose relationship to the published essay are unclear are not included at this stage of our work.
  - The village of Jericho, between 1858 and 1888; loc.06029; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box OV 11, Folder 1888, "Elias Hicks")
    This one-page prose draft regarding the birthplace of Elias Hicks was likely one of the manuscripts from which Whitman fashioned his 1888 essay Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, first published in November Boughs and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The reference to Elias Hicks's daughter Martha Hicks Aldrich as "still living" suggests that Whitman began writing this manuscript before 1862, the year of Martha's death. The reference, in the revision of this passage, to her death "a year or two ago," "about 1863," would seem to indicate that at least that portion of the manuscript was written around 1865. Whitman planned to write an essay about Elias Hicks for many years. While finishing preparations for the printing of November Boughs, Whitman told Horace Traubel, "Some of these bits were written as many as thirty years ago. Some of them I have written within the past year. They are a miscellaneous lot but they all belong in the same stream." (See Traubel, With Walt Whitman in Camden, 2: 42.) The present manuscript is stored together with many other manuscripts on the topics of Elias Hicks and Quakerism. Those that directly contributed to the published essay are described separately. Those whose relationship to the published essay are unclear are not included at this stage of our work.
  - an ardent temperament, between 1858 and 1888; loc.06025; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box OV 11, Folder 1888, "Elias Hicks")
    Two manuscript leaves pasted to a backing scrap to create a continuous inscribed surface. The notes here about Elias Hicks's early life probably contributed to Whitman's 1888 essay Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, first published in November Boughs and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Whitman planned to write an essay about Elias Hicks for many years. While finishing preparations for the printing of November Boughs, Whitman told Horace Traubel, "Some of these bits were written as many as thirty years ago. Some of them I have written within the past year. They are a miscellaneous lot but they all belong in the same stream." (See Traubel, With Walt Whitman in Camden, 2: 42.) The present manuscript is stored together with many other manuscripts on the topics of Elias Hicks and Quakerism. Those that directly contributed to the published essay are described separately. Those whose relationship to the published essay are unclear are not included at this stage of our work.